<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-09-04T16:47:01+09:00</updated><id>https://ramos-ramos.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ramos &amp;amp; Ramos</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">a cursory look into the last 10 years of the npb draft</title><link href="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/npb-draft/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a cursory look into the last 10 years of the npb draft"/><published>2024-10-24T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-10-24T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/npb-draft</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/npb-draft/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/npb_draft/npb_draft-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/npb_draft/npb_draft-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/npb_draft/npb_draft-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/npb_draft/npb_draft" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="the-pick-is-in">The pick is in…</h2> <p>It’s pretty safe to say that drafting is one of several keys to success in running a baseball team. Teams need to be able to identify talent that they can develop and who can produce for them down the line. Drafting may be even more important in NPB, as blockbuster trades are a rarity and there are very few medium to high impact free agents every offseason. Aside from signing international players and the rule 5 draft, drafting players is the biggest way to bring in new talent.</p> <p>So if drafting is so crucial to success, it stands to reason that teams put a conscious effort into the way they draft. So how do they draft? What positions do they tend to draft? What types of teams do they draft players from the most? High school? College? What about the first round?</p> <p>We take a look at the past 10 years of the NPB draft try to find very preliminary answers to these kinds of questions. Don’t expect groundbreaking revelations, everything here is quite cursory.</p> <h2 id="types-of-teams-players-are-drafted-from">Types of teams players are drafted from</h2> <p>We break players down into six types according to the type of team they were drafted from:</p> <ul> <li>High school players</li> <li>College players</li> <li>Industrial league players</li> <li>Independent league players</li> <li>Amateur club plauers</li> <li>Players from other types of teams</li> </ul> <p>High schoolers (e.g. Roki Sasaki, Munetaka Murakami), college players (e.g. Masato Morishita, Natsuki Takeuchi), industrial league players (e.g. Kojiro Yoshimura, Ryuki Watarai), and indie leaguers are generally the most heard of. We throw in a category for amateur clubs (industrial leagues are grouped together with amateur clubs under the Japanese Amateur Baseball Association) and an et cetera “other” category for the remaining players.</p> <p>One disclaimer is that the categorization of players may be a little inaccurate. We used a list of existing collegiate and amateur clubs and a handful of heuristics to sort the players into teams, so there may be some errors.</p> <h3 id="what-kinds-of-teams-are-players-drafted-from">What kinds of teams are players drafted from?</h3> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/team_type.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Overall, teams tend to draft high schoolers, however in the first round they tend to draft college players.</div> <p>In the above figure we have the distribution of drafted players from the last 10 years over the type of team they were drafted from. Moving forward we consider the following “splits”:</p> <ul> <li>Entire Draft: The entire draft, both the standard draft and the developmental draft.</li> <li>Standard Draft: Just the main draft, excluding the developmental draft.</li> <li>Developmental Draft: As the name implies, only the developmental draft that occurs after the main draft.</li> <li>First Round: Like in a lot of other sports, many high impact players (e.g. Roki Sasaki, Hiroya Miyagi) are drafted in the first round.</li> </ul> <p>Right off the bat, there aren’t many players from amateur clubs. Only three such players have been drafted, all in the developmental draft, and none of them have had a single game on the top team. There are also only one “other” player who doesn’t fall into any of the main categories: Gosuke Katoh, who was drafted by the Nippon Ham-Fighters while a member of the New York Mets. Leave it to the Fighters to do something as unprecendented as this.</p> <p>As we can see in the figure, in the entire draft, both the standard draft and the developmental one, high school players dominate, averaging a lead of 16.1% over the next prominent category, college players. However the story changes dramatically when we consider only first round picks, where it’s actually college players who have the lion’s share at 49.2% over high school players at 40.7%. On a side-note, no one goes for industrial players past the main draft.</p> <p><strong><em>Takeaway: High school players are popular in general, but college players are favored in the first round</em></strong></p> <h3 id="how-do-the-kinds-of-teams-players-are-drafted-from-change-per-round">How do the kinds of teams players are drafted from change per round?</h3> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/team_type_round.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">In the main draft, college players go more in the earlier rounds then give way to high school talents. In the developmental draft, high schoolers lead in every round.</div> <p>We plot the number of players drafted per round for each type of team in the standard and developmental drafts. We can see that college players are more frequently drafted not only in the first round of the main draft but in the second round too. It’s in the third round where high schoolers take over and dominate the draft in the middle rounds. Industrial players and indie leaguers are drafted at relatively unchanging amounts, with industrial leaguers consistently being drafted more and indie leaguers only being drafted starting the second round. As expected, as the draft goes on, less drafting occurs across the board.</p> <p>Things change when we turn to the developmental draft, where high school players are the most frequently drafter type of of player for most of the rounds. Collegiate players and indie leaguers stay fairly toe-to-toe below.</p> <p><strong><em>Takeaway: In the standard draft, college players in the earlier rounds, high schoolers in the later ones. In the developmental draft, high school players all the way.</em></strong></p> <h3 id="how-do-the-kinds-of-teams-players-are-drafted-from-change-per-year">How do the kinds of teams players are drafted from change per year?</h3> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/team_type_year.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">The number of high schoolers and college players in the main draft have become similar while high schoolers have increased in the developmental draft.</div> <p>Over the entire draft, high school players tend to be drafted more than college players every year. There has only been one year when the number of high school draftees and college ones were separated by less than nine players. However, when we look at the standard draft, while high school players have been drafted more than college players by wider margins from 2016-2019, starting 2020 the number of high school draftees dip while the number of college draftees rise, leaving them neck-in-neck from 2020 to 2023. If high school and college players are being drafted at similar amounts in recent years, why do high schoolers still outnumber college players overall? In the development draft, starting 2018, there has been a general rise of drafted high schoolers, from 9 players in 2018 to 26 playres in 2023.</p> <p>Focusing on the first round, contrary to expectation, college players are not consistently picked more in the first round than high school players. In five of the last years, college draftees have only outnumbered high school draftees by at most only one player. The reason why collegiate athletes tend to be drafted more overall is that in three of the last ten years, there have were eight college players drafted in the first round to only three to four high schoolers. High school players were drafted more than collegiate ones in the first round on two occasions, which were three years apart. The first was in 2016, where six high schoolers were drafted to five college players. However, in the second instance in 2019, seven high school players were drafted compared to only one collegiate player, with a record (in the 10 year sample) four industrial league players. The 2019 draft class was stacked with high school pitchers, including Yasunobu Okugawa, Hiroya Miyagi, and Roki Sasaki. The lone college athlete? Masato Morishita. Seems as if the Carp still picked well.</p> <p><strong><em>Takeaway: In recent years, high schoolers and college players have been drafted in similar numbers, while in the developmental draft the number of high school draft picks has been increasing.</em></strong></p> <h2 id="positions-of-drafted-players">Positions of drafted players</h2> <p>We break players down into the following positions:</p> <ul> <li>Pitcher</li> <li>Infiedler</li> <li>Outfielder</li> <li>Catcher</li> </ul> <p>We do not distinguish between types of infielders (1B, 2B, SS, 3B).</p> <h3 id="how-are-players-drafted-by-position">How are players drafted by position?</h3> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/position.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Pitchers are the most drafted position in all ways of looking at the draft.</div> <p>Unsurprisingly, pitchers dominate in all splits of the draft. Especially in the first round, where they comprise 69.2% of draft picks.</p> <p>Bottom line is, teams need lots of pitchers. Healthy fielders can play every day, but starting pitchers even when healthy can only pitch around once a week. Could it perhaps also be that Japan simply just has that much pitching talent? One would have to compare these distributions to those of other leagues to get an idea.</p> <p><strong><em>Takeaway: Pitchers, pitchers, pitchers.</em></strong></p> <h3 id="how-do-the-positions-of-drafted-players-change-per-round">How do the positions of drafted players change per round?</h3> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/position_round.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Pitchers tend to be the most drafted per round.</div> <p>Last time we did a per round plot, we noticed that while high schoolers were generally the most frequently drafted, they were more drafted specifically in the middle to lower rounds. Could there be a similar pattern for pitchers? We don’t observe that, as the plot shows that pitchers are not only the most drafted position in the draft, but also tend to be the most drafted position per round.</p> <p><strong><em>Takeaway: Pitchers, still.</em></strong></p> <h3 id="how-do-the-positions-of-drafted-players-change-per-year">How do the positions of drafted players change per year?</h3> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/position_year.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">There's been an uptick in the number of pitchers drafted in the developmental draft in recent years.</div> <p>As previously established, year in and year out pitchers tend to be the most drafted, however in the developmental draft starting 2020 there was a further increase in the number of pitchers drafted each year. I’m not much of a NPB historian, so I can’t say why this happend. Perhaps there was a rule change or some sort, or a team got a new draft-happy GM? Honestly the answer’s probably out there, I’m just too lazy to search it up.</p> <p>Pitchers dominating the first round is also consistent here, as there was only one year in the past decade where less than seven pitchers were drafted in the first round.</p> <p><strong><em>Takeaway: More developmental draft pitchers lately.</em></strong></p> <h2 id="teams-against-players-drafted-from-them">Teams against players drafted from them</h2> <h3 id="how-many-teams-have-had-a-certain-number-of-players-drafted-from-them">How many teams have had a certain number of players drafted from them?</h3> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/teams_against_drafted_from.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">A majority of teams only produce only one draft pick.</div> <p>We plot the number of teams who have produced a certain number of drafted players for a range of drafted players. Of the 472 teams, 260 of them (55.1%) have only produced one player drafted by an NPB team. Because the draftee-producing teams are primarily composed of those who have only put out one pick, moving forward, if might be more useful to visualize only teams which have produced more than a certain threshold of draft picks.</p> <p><strong><em>Takeaway: Most teams only produce one drafted player.</em></strong></p> <h3 id="who-are-the-top-teams-at-producing-draftees">Who are the top teams at producing draftees?</h3> <p>Rather than rank the top <em>x</em> teams by number of players drafted from them, we’ll instead show all teams that produced at least <em>x</em> draft picks.</p> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/top_teams_draft.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Mostly colleges, but a lots of Indigo Socks</div> <p>Looking at all teams who have produced at least 10 draftees, we can see that NPB really, really loves the Tokushima Indigo Socks. They lead all teams with 25 draft picks produced, 7 more than the two teams tied for second (Meiji University and Asia University), which only lead the third highest-producing team by 3 players. Interstingly, the Tokushima Indigo Socks are the only independent league team. With the exception of two industrial league teams (JR East Tohoku and Toyota) and two high school teams (Osaka Toin and Hanasaki Tokuharu), the remaining nine teams are all colleges.</p> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/top_teams_std_draft.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Less Indigo Socks, and still mainly colleges</div> <p>Focusing on the standard draft, again with only teams with at least 10 draftees, we see that the Tokushima Indigo Socks have fallen to only 10 players. Instead we have Asia University and Meiji University tied at the top with 17 players each. Both leading industrial league teams are still there, but Osaka Toin is the only high school to produce at least 10 picks in the standard draft. Like with the overall draft, most of the teams here are universities, comprising 7 of the 11 teams that met the threshold.</p> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/top_teams_dev_draft.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Mainly indie league teams, especially the Indigo Socks.</div> <p>Going to the developmental draft, and lowering our threshold to only five players, we see while high schoolers mainly comprise the developmental draft as established previously, it’s actually independent league teams that produce the most players per team. Furthermore, we can see here how the Tokushima Indigo Socks ended up dominating the overall draft: no other team has produced more than 7 draftees, while the Indigo Socks lead with 15.</p> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/top_teams_first_round.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="400px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Mostly Meiji University.</div> <p>Lastly, looking only at the first round with a threshold of two players, Meiji University really pulls away from the pack. They have produced 8 first round draft picks, while the next best teams (Osaka Toin, Waseda University, and Toyo University) only have 4. Not every one of their draft picks have panned out to be super successful, but they did produce Masato Morishita, Sachiya Yamasaki, and Yuya Yanagi.</p> <p>Osaka Toin’s also interesting to look at as they’re the only high school to have more than the threshold (the other high schools only meet it) with four draftees. The only one with a lot of hype at the moment is <a href="https://twitter.com/yakyucosmo/status/1742538964089901430">NPB #2 prospect Shion Mastsuo</a>, but we’ve haven’t seen too much yet from Softbank’s 2023 first round pick Yugo Maeda either, so perhaps things will change down the road.</p> <p>Another thing to note here is that both JR East Tohoko and Toyota, while producing several picks in the draft overall, have not produced multiple first round picks. Instead we have Toshiba (Kojiro Yoshimura’s having an excellent sophomore campaign), Osaka Gas (Koji Chikamoto was a big contributor to Hanshin’s championship last year), and Yamaha.</p> <p><strong><em>Takeaways: Colleges all around, Indigo Socks in the developmental draft, Meiji University in the first round.</em></strong></p> <h2 id="team-tendencies">Team Tendencies</h2> <h3 id="how-do-npb-teams-draft-according-to-draftee-team">How do NPB teams draft according to draftee team?</h3> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/team_type_npb.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="1024px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"></div> <p>Teams tend to draft high schoolers, especially the Hawks at 63.2%. Only the Tigers have drafted without picking high school players the most at 34.3%, with the Lions splitting even between high school and collegiate draftees as 36.6% a piece.</p> <p>Second place is usually college players, although the Orix Buffaloes have drafted the same number of college and industrial players.</p> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/team_type_npb_std.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="1024px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"></div> <p>This trend for the most part continues when focusing specifically on the standard draft, although more teams, namely the Eagles, Baystars, and Lions, draft more collegiate players than high school ones. Orix’s tendency to draft industiral players shines even more here, as they are the only team to have industrial players constitute the second larget subset of draftees.</p> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/team_type_npb_dev.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="1024px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"></div> <p>Developmental draft picks are also mostly high schoolers, but it should be noted that some teams draft much fewer players in the developmental rounds. Notable exceptions include the Tigers (6 of 9 players being collegiate), Swallows (6 of 12 being indie leaguers), and Dragons (9 of 24 being indie leaguers).</p> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/team_type_npb_first_round.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="1024px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"></div> <p>First round distributions per team are mostly aligned with what we found earlier, which was that college players tend to be drafted the most often in the first round. That being said, the Hawks really buck the trend, here, having only drafted two college players in the first round in the past decade, one of which is actually current Fighters reliever Seigi Tanaka. Instead, they spent 7 of their last 10 first round selections on high school talent. The Marines also drafted more high school players than college players, while the Orix Buffaloes, Yakult Swallows, and Chunichi Dragons drafted the same number of high schoolers as collegiate athletes in a 10-year span.</p> <p><strong><em>Takeaways: Mostly the same patterns, but with some exceptions.</em></strong></p> <h3 id="how-do-npb-teams-draft-according-to-position">How do NPB teams draft according to position?</h3> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/position_npb.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="1024px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"></div> <p>When looking according to position, the same general trend of pitcher’s first holds. Every team has spent more than 52% of their draft picks across both draft types on pitching, though this will come as a surprise to no one. The only other thing of note here is that the Tigers have drafted more outfielders than infielders compared to everyone else, though only marginally.</p> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/position_npb_std.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="1024px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"></div> <p>There…really isn’t much else to say about the standard draft per team that hasn’t already been discussed. It’s pitchers, infielders, then a toss-up between outfielders and catchers. There could be more going on here, but this is only a cursory look so I’ll leave that to any future investigation.</p> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/position_npb_dev.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="1024px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"></div> <p>Like in previous findings, pitchers, while still usually the most dominantly drafted position in the developmental draft, takes a backseat, usually sitting under 50%. The Dragons though seem to be an outlier, with 70.8% of their 24 developmental draft players being pitchers.</p> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/position_npb_first_round.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="1024px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"></div> <p>Again, while teams take the foot off the gas a little for pitchers in the developmental draft, it’s pedal to the metal for first round picks. Nine of the twelve teams in NPB have at least seven pitchers taken in the first round. For the heck of it, let’s try to list down one <strong><em>notable</em></strong> (arguable) first round pitcher for as many teams as possible.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Team</th> <th>Notable Pitcher Taken in the First Round from 2014-2023</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Orix Buffaloes</td> <td>Hiroya Miyagi</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Chiba Lotte Marines</td> <td>Roki Sasaki</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Fukuoka Softbank Hawks</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>Tohoku Rakuten Golden Eagles</td> <td>Takahisa Hayakawa</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Saitama Seibu Lions</td> <td>Tatsuya Imai</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Hokkaido Nippon Ham-Fighters</td> <td>Hiromi Itoh</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Hanshin Tigers</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>Hiroshima Toyo Carp</td> <td>Ryoji Kurabayashi</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Yokohama DeNA Baystars</td> <td>Shota Imanaga</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Yomiuri Giants</td> <td>Taisei</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Tokyo Yakult Swallows</td> <td>Yasunobu Okugawa</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Chunichi Dragons</td> <td>Hiroto Takahashi</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>The point is there’s a lot of high-impact pitching already known to teams by the first round. I mean, just look at this list. That’s restricting teams to one pitcher. Case in point, the Buffaloes have drafted Hiroya Miyagi, Shunpeita Yamashita, and Ryuhei Sotani all in the first round, not to mention Ren Mukunoki should he ever return to form.</p> <p><strong><em>Takeaways: Mostly the same patterns.</em></strong></p> <h2 id="a-cursory-picture">A cursory picture</h2> <div class="l-page" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_draft/npb_breakdown.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="1024px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"></div> <p>While not particularly legible, thought it would be fun to shove a sunburst at the end of all this. Here you can see each teams draft picks broken down into position, then team type, then team. Although it doesn’t synthesize all the points we discussed, it does repeat the ideas that:</p> <ul> <li>Teams usually draft among high school and collegiate talent</li> <li>Within these talent pools, they draft a lot of pitchers</li> </ul> <p>Again, none of these aren’t particularly surprising as I would assume most developable talent are among students, and that we really do need a lot of pitching.</p> <p>Furthermore, as much of a cop out conclusion as it is, we haven’t been able to tie any possible differences in drafting strategy, if they’re even statistically significant in the first place, to the results we see on the field. For example, is there anything in Orix’s draft distributions that tie into their pitching lab?</p> <p>It would be nice to gain deeper insights, but as stated before, this is merely a cursory look into the past decade of drafting.</p>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Ramos</name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="baseball"/><category term="npb"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[what does a decade of drafting tell us?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">into the lion’s den: statline scouting the seibu lions farm’s pitchers</title><link href="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/seibu-statline-scouting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="into the lion’s den: statline scouting the seibu lions farm’s pitchers"/><published>2024-06-29T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-06-29T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/seibu-statline-scouting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/seibu-statline-scouting/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/seibu_statline_scouting/seibu_statline_scouting-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/seibu_statline_scouting/seibu_statline_scouting-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/seibu_statline_scouting/seibu_statline_scouting-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/seibu_statline_scouting/seibu_statline_scouting.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="into-the-lions-den">Into the lion’s den</h2> <p>Tatsuya Imai. Kaima Taira. Kona Takahashi. Chihiro Sumida. The Saitama Seibu Lion’s pitching lab has produced a stacked rotation. This is all without mentioning PL ROY frontrunner Natsuki Takeuchi and their <a href="https://twitter.com/yakyucosmo/status/1742538964089901430">NPB #4 prospect “the Randy Johnson of Japan” Shinnosuke Hada</a>. With this incoming youth movement, the question is: just how deep does the lion’s den go?</p> <p>We take a crack at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KHR6ODadQJ8&amp;list=PL3lJFzNSaN7RHuqCVSue8ewUx8lqyZkjU">Foolish Bailey-style Statline Scouting</a> the Lions farm looking for pitching prospects. In the spirit of statline scouting, we’ll be excluding the most intuitive choices, Natsuki Takeuchi and Shinnosuke Hada.</p> <p><em>All advanced stats are as of June 16, 2024. Other data like game logs may go past that.</em></p> <h2 id="1-shinya-sugai">1. Shinya Sugai</h2> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: left">Player</th> <th style="text-align: right">Age</th> <th style="text-align: left">Pos.</th> <th style="text-align: right">IP</th> <th style="text-align: right">FIP</th> <th style="text-align: right">FIP-</th> <th style="text-align: right">K%</th> <th style="text-align: right">BB%</th> <th style="text-align: right">K-BB%</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Shinya Sugai</td> <td style="text-align: right">20</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">44</td> <td style="text-align: right"><strong>2.57</strong></td> <td style="text-align: right">70</td> <td style="text-align: right">24.9</td> <td style="text-align: right">7.2</td> <td style="text-align: right"><strong>17.7</strong></td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Shinnosuke Hada</td> <td style="text-align: right">20</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">31</td> <td style="text-align: right">2.91</td> <td style="text-align: right">79</td> <td style="text-align: right">26.3</td> <td style="text-align: right">12.7</td> <td style="text-align: right">13.6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Haruki Sugiyama</td> <td style="text-align: right">18</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">17</td> <td style="text-align: right">3.01</td> <td style="text-align: right">82</td> <td style="text-align: right">17.5</td> <td style="text-align: right">1.6</td> <td style="text-align: right">15.9</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Kaito Yoza</td> <td style="text-align: right">28</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">51.3</td> <td style="text-align: right">3.42</td> <td style="text-align: right">93</td> <td style="text-align: right">12.4</td> <td style="text-align: right">5.7</td> <td style="text-align: right">6.7</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Towa Uema</td> <td style="text-align: right">23</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">32</td> <td style="text-align: right">3.52</td> <td style="text-align: right">96</td> <td style="text-align: right">12</td> <td style="text-align: right">6</td> <td style="text-align: right">6</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>The most obvious thing to do is simply to sort by a strong performance-indicator like FIP or something adjacent like K-BB%. Filtering to pitchers with at least 15 IP, it turns out that the top performers on the Lions farm are actually the same person. And perhaps surprisingly, it’s not their top prospect Shinnosuke Hada. The Lions’ farm leader in FIP and K-BB% is 20-year-old Shinya Sugai, a 2021 3rd round developmental (<em>ikusei</em>) draft pick. This year Sugai has skimmed his BB% from 8.7 to 7.2 and bumped his K% from 18.5 to 24.9. A 24.9 K% and 17.7 K-BB% might not be off-the-scale numbers, but his 2.57 FIP is good for a 70 FIP-. Note that his K% is second only to Hada, and Sugai walks less batters.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/seibu_statline_scouting/farm_k-bb.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Sugai’s K-BB% is good even compared to players outside of the Seibu Lions.</div> <p>Sugai is not only impressive within his own team, but also across the entire farm level of NPB. Among farm pitchers with at least 25 IP, Sugai is in the 96th percentile in K-BB%.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/seibu_statline_scouting/sugai_np_ip.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Sugai could still work on his efficiency.</div> <p>One thing to bear in mind is that Sugai has issues with pitching deep into games, usually reaching 90+ pitches by the end of the 5th inning and making it to the 6th inning or further on only 2 out of 10 appearances on the farm. Furthermore, Sugai already has made an appearance on the top team, where he struggled against major league hitting, giving up 4 walks to his 4 strikeouts alongside a home run over 5 innings in a start.</p> <h2 id="2-haruki-sugiyama">2. Haruki Sugiyama</h2> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: left">Player</th> <th style="text-align: right">Age</th> <th style="text-align: left">Pos.</th> <th style="text-align: right">IP</th> <th style="text-align: right">FIP</th> <th style="text-align: right">xFIP</th> <th style="text-align: right">K%</th> <th style="text-align: right">BB%</th> <th style="text-align: right">K-BB%</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Haruki Sugiyama</td> <td style="text-align: right">18</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">17</td> <td style="text-align: right">3.01</td> <td style="text-align: right"><strong>2.74</strong></td> <td style="text-align: right">17.5</td> <td style="text-align: right"><strong>1.6</strong></td> <td style="text-align: right">15.9</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Kaito Yoza</td> <td style="text-align: right">28</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">51.3</td> <td style="text-align: right">3.42</td> <td style="text-align: right">3.72</td> <td style="text-align: right">12.4</td> <td style="text-align: right">5.7</td> <td style="text-align: right">6.7</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Uema Towa</td> <td style="text-align: right">23</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">32</td> <td style="text-align: right">3.52</td> <td style="text-align: right">3.56</td> <td style="text-align: right">12</td> <td style="text-align: right">6</td> <td style="text-align: right">6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Shinya Sugai</td> <td style="text-align: right">20</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">44</td> <td style="text-align: right">2.57</td> <td style="text-align: right">2.83</td> <td style="text-align: right">24.9</td> <td style="text-align: right">7.2</td> <td style="text-align: right">17.7</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Yuto Akagami</td> <td style="text-align: right">25</td> <td style="text-align: left">RP</td> <td style="text-align: right">18</td> <td style="text-align: right">4.48</td> <td style="text-align: right">4.99</td> <td style="text-align: right">6.8</td> <td style="text-align: right">8.1</td> <td style="text-align: right">-1.4</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/seibu_statline_scouting/sugiyama_k_bb.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Sugiyama may not strike out as many batters as Hada or Sugai, but he keeps the walks so low that he’s second in K-BB%.</div> <p>Another thing to try is to see who has the lowest walk-rate. Who’s avoiding free base-runners the most? With the same minimum 15 IP among Lions farm pitchers, it’s not Hada again, and neither is it Sugai. 2023 3rd rounder Haruki Sugiyama leads the farm with a 1.6 BB% at just 18 years old, which incidentally gives him the second highest K-BB% at 15.9. He also happens to lead in xFIP at 2.74. While he’s not striking out batters at a significant clip, across 3 games on the farm where he’s gone at least 5 innings deep each, he’s given up only 1 walk. What Sugiyama lacks in stuff, he makes up for in control</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/seibu_statline_scouting/farm_bb.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Sugiyama’s control stands out even compared to the rest of NPB’s farm.</div> <p>If we were to widen our scope to the entire NPB farm system, Sugiyama’s control is still evident, with him ranking in the 97th percentile in walk rate among pitchers with at least 15 IP.</p> <h2 id="3-towa-uema">3. Towa Uema</h2> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: left">Player</th> <th style="text-align: right">Age</th> <th style="text-align: left">Pos.</th> <th style="text-align: right">IP</th> <th style="text-align: right">FIP</th> <th style="text-align: right">xFIP</th> <th style="text-align: right">FIP-</th> <th style="text-align: right">xFIP-</th> <th style="text-align: right">GB%</th> <th style="text-align: right">OFFB%</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Towa Uema</td> <td style="text-align: right">23</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">32</td> <td style="text-align: right">3.52</td> <td style="text-align: right">3.56</td> <td style="text-align: right">96</td> <td style="text-align: right">97</td> <td style="text-align: right">53.6</td> <td style="text-align: right">32.6</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Hiroki Inoue</td> <td style="text-align: right">22</td> <td style="text-align: left">RP</td> <td style="text-align: right">15</td> <td style="text-align: right">3.77</td> <td style="text-align: right">4.12</td> <td style="text-align: right">102</td> <td style="text-align: right">112</td> <td style="text-align: right">50.9</td> <td style="text-align: right">28</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Minato Aoyama</td> <td style="text-align: right">23</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">49</td> <td style="text-align: right">4.2</td> <td style="text-align: right">4.03</td> <td style="text-align: right">114</td> <td style="text-align: right">109</td> <td style="text-align: right">52.8</td> <td style="text-align: right">30.7</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left">Yutaro Watanabe</td> <td style="text-align: right">23</td> <td style="text-align: left">SP</td> <td style="text-align: right">24</td> <td style="text-align: right">4.28</td> <td style="text-align: right">4.63</td> <td style="text-align: right">116</td> <td style="text-align: right">126</td> <td style="text-align: right">54.9</td> <td style="text-align: right">28.4</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Aside from strikeouts and walks, we can also take a look at batted ball distributions. If we filter to Lions farm pitchers with a minimum 15 IP who have a GB% over 50 and an OFFB% less than or equal to 33, only 2019 7th round pick Towa Uema has a FIP- and xFIP- below 100. While the 23-year-old isn’t putting up the gaudiest strikeout and walk numbers, his ability to keep batted balls more on the ground and less in the air has helped him get to a 2.12 ERA.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/seibu_statline_scouting/uema_gb_offb_ip.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">If you discount the lack of IP in 2023, Uema’s batted ball distribution is getting better and better.</div> <p>It’s hard to evaluate whether Uema truly fits the profile of a groundball pitcher since he missed 2022 with elbow surgery and only pitched 12 2/3 last year, but across his last three seasons, his GB% has consistently gone up (44.3 → 47.6 → 53.6) while his OFFB% has consistently gone down (41.1 → 37.3 → 32.6). He’s also currently putting up the best walk rate of his career at 6 BB%.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/seibu_statline_scouting/farm_gb_offb.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Uema is one of a select group with ≤ 33 GB% and &gt;50 OFFB%.</div> <p>Uema’s batted ball profile puts him among the 20% of all farm pitchers with at least 25 IP who have a GB% greater than 50 and an OFFB% less than or equal to 33. His GB% lies in the 90th percentile while his OFFB% is in the 81st percentile.</p> <h2 id="rotation-of-the-future">Rotation of the future?</h2> <p>It’s important to remember that these are all prospects. They may pan out, they may not. But one thing for sure is that they’re putting up interesting numbers down on the farm. It’s certainly fun to think that perhaps one day, these pitchers will contribute to keeping the Saitama Seibu Lions a fearsome, dangerous lion’s den.</p> <h3 id="data-sources">Data Sources:</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://bo-no05.hatenadiary.org/">ぼおのの日記</a></li> <li><a href="https://sp.baseball.findfriends.jp/">ベースボール週刊</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Ramos</name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="baseball"/><category term="npb"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[in the jungle, the mighty jungle, the lion sleeps tonight. but which lions are YOU sleeping on?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">orix pitching lab goes brrr: 5 new(ish) buffaloes pitchers to keep an eye on this year</title><link href="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/orix-pitching-lab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="orix pitching lab goes brrr: 5 new(ish) buffaloes pitchers to keep an eye on this year"/><published>2024-06-18T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-06-18T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/orix-pitching-lab</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/orix-pitching-lab/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/orix_pitching_lab-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/orix_pitching_lab-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/orix_pitching_lab-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/orix_pitching_lab.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="welcome-to-the-pitching-lab">Welcome to the pitching lab</h2> <p>No one was particularly worried about the Orix Buffaloes pitching when they posted back-to-back-to-back Sawamura Award winner, PL triple crown winner, and PL MVP Yoshinobu Yamamoto, primarily because they have a pitching lab. Just last year fireballer Shunpeita Yamashita made his top team debut and went on to win 2023 PL ROY. Not to mention they also have 2021 ROY Hiroya Miyagi, who prior to straining his chest was carrying a 1.89 FIP and a 24.3 K-BB% this year. Kohei Azuma even climbed his way to the top team as a developmental draft pick, becoming the first pitcher to start their career with winning 7 consecutive decisions en route to starting Game 3 of the 2023 Japan Series.</p> <p>As a pitching lab, the Buffaloes are more or less continuing to put out arms. Whether they’ll all pan out we’ve yet to see, but here are five new(ish) Orix pitchers that might be interesting to keep on eye for the rest of 2024.</p> <p>Some disclaimers before we continue:</p> <ol> <li> <p>None of these names are surprising. If you follow <a href="https://twitter.com/yakyucosmo">Yakyu Cosmopolitan</a>, you’ll have definitely heard of these names. It’s still interesting however that these are not players who played regularly on the top team last season.</p> </li> <li> <p>We are far, far from anything even remotely resembling a player evaluator. Don’t expect any cool discussions about the shape of their fastball or how they improved their mechanics this offseason or anything like that (we certainly wish we were smart enough to talk about those things).</p> </li> <li> <p>Just to be clear, we’re not running an Orix fan page here. We like players, not teams, and Orix just happens to produce a lot of players we find interesting.</p> </li> </ol> <h2 id="1-the-obvious-one-ryuhei-sotani">1. The obvious one: Ryuhei Sotani</h2> <div class="row mt-3 l-screen"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/sotani-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/sotani-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/sotani-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/sotani.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Where else to start other than Ryuhei Sotani. Yakyu Cosmopolitan had Sotani pegged as the No. 3 overall prospect and Orix’s No. 1 prospect coming into this season, although he’s already graduated by now.</p> <center> <div class="jekyll-twitter-plugin"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="ja" dir="ltr">My Top 50 NPB Prospects in 2024<br/><br/>個人的な2024年NPBプロスペクト ランキング <a href="https://t.co/kXDfqSFGSE">pic.twitter.com/kXDfqSFGSE</a></p>&mdash; Yakyu Cosmopolitan (@yakyucosmo) <a href="https://twitter.com/yakyucosmo/status/1742538964089901430?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 3, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </div> </center> <p>Sotani was Orix’s first round draft pick in 2022, and started only 7 games in 2023. This season marks his first a full-fledged member of the rotation, where he’s been helping Anderson Espinoza and Luis Castillo carry the load for an Orix rotation that has lost Yamamoto (MLB), Miyagi (injured), Yamashita (who was working out some things on the farm, but just came back recently), Yamasaki (Nippon-Ham), and Yamaoka (injured to start the season).</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/orix_pitching_lab/orix_rotation.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="550px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Sotani has been one of the best domestic starters in Orix's rotation with Miyagi out.</div> <p>Of the rotation they’ve had in May since Miyagi’s injury, he’s been the best domestic Orix starter with at least 30 IP in terms of FIP, xFIP, K%, and BB% (Miyagi would lead if he was still in). He’s also pushed his K/9 to 9.2 thanks to his June 11 start of 6 IP, 0 ER, 12 K. Needless to say, the kid is shoving.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/orix_pitching_lab/npb_lhp_fb.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Among lefities, minimum 100 fastball thrown, Sotani's fastball is in the 80th percentile in terms of velocity.</div> <p>What else makes Sotani so special, aside from being the latest Orix whiz kid? He throws 92 mph, which in Japan is apparently already quite good for a lefty. He’s 80th percentile in fastball velo for left handed pitchers with at least 100 fastballs thrown.</p> <p>All-in-all, Sotani looks to take the torch from Shunpeita Yamashita as the poster boy of the Orix pitching lab.</p> <h2 id="2-the-prospect-kyosuke-saito">2. The prospect: Kyosuke Saito</h2> <div class="row mt-3 l-screen"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/saito-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/saito-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/saito-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/saito.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/orix_pitching_lab/orix_starters.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="550" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Because he is not a full-time member of Orix's starting, Kyosuke Saito does not have innings under his belt. However in his very small sample size, he has been quite effective.</div> <p>If Ryuhei Sotani has already graduated, who is now Orix’s No. 1 prospect? That would be Kyosuke Saito, who was drafted two rounds after Sotani back in 2022. He pitched 4 IP in 2023, and has gotten more starts in 2024, where he a currently has a 0.47 ERA and 0.83 WHIP, and is holding opponents to a 0.373 OPS over a small sample size of 19 1/3 IP.</p> <p>His sub-1.00 ERA may not last long as he’s got a 44.00 OFFB% on the top team and a 43.6 OFFB% as a starter on the farm in a similar sample size, but again these samples might be small.</p> <p>Saito’s still a prospect and as such may be expected to grow further still, but if he can maintain his current success and fully break out, perhaps we could be looking at the newest full-time member of the Orix rotation.</p> <h2 id="3-the-rookie-seiryu-kotajima">3. The rookie: Seiryu Kotajima</h2> <div class="row mt-3 l-screen"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/kotajima-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/kotajima-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/kotajima-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/kotajima.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Success from lower round draft picks aren’t unheard of, but they’re always interesting to see. Ryuhei Sotani was a first rounder, and Kyosuke Saito was a third rounder, but rookie Seiryu Kotajima is a 2023 sixth round draft pick who’s already finding playing time on the top team.</p> <p>Orix doesn’t only have elite starters, but they’ve also put out lights-out relievers as well, such as Yuki Udagawa and Soichiro Yamazaki. Udagawa and Yamazaki haven’t been playing as much this season, but Kotajima’s been holding down the fort in spectacular fashion, starting his career with 21 scoreless pitching appearances. While a 0.00 ERA obviously isn’t sustainable, his 3.06 FIP is still good for a 94 FIP-.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/orix_pitching_lab/orix_bullpen.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Even if his 0.00 ERA can't continue forever, Kotajima's FIP is still competitive among Orix bullpen arms and he's consuming innings while doing it. Only an NPB veteran (Kazutomo Iguchi) and an MLB veteran (Andres Machado) players have better FIP and more innings. Remember, Kotajima is keeping up as a rookie.</div> <p>Even if Seiryu Kotajima may be experiencing some luck right now, it looks like Orix have found a new shut down option for their bullpen this season.</p> <h2 id="4-the-comeback-kid-ren-mukunoki">4. The comeback kid: Ren Mukunoki</h2> <div class="row mt-3 l-screen"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/mukunoki-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/mukunoki-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/mukunoki-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/mukunoki.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Orix’s 2021 first round draft pick Ren Mukunoki started hot out the gate in 2022, pitching to a 1.02 ERA across four starts (one being one out away from a no-hitter) before needing Tommy John surgery.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/orix_pitching_lab/orix_farm_fip_mukunoki.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Mukunoki has been hard at work on the farm since coming back from Tommy John.</div> <p>Mukunoki’s now back in 2024 and has posted a 2.08 ERA, 2.62 FIP, 2.97 xFIP, and a 5% BB% on the farm across 37 IP. However, he unfortunately couldn’t replicate that success in a lone start on the top team, giving up 4 ER over 3 IP.</p> <p>While we still need to see more of him on the top team, his underlying numbers hopefully show that he has indeed returned to form, making him a player to keep on eye on for the rest of 2024.</p> <h2 id="5-the-unproven-kazuma-satoh">5. The unproven: Kazuma Satoh</h2> <div class="row mt-3 l-screen"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/satoh-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/satoh-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/satoh-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/satoh.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>If you thought Orix finding relative success with a sixth rounder was impressive, wait until you hear about Kazuma Satoh.</p> <p>There are only two people who have pitched more innings than Ren Mukunoki on the farm, and one of them has a 3.78 ERA. The other one is Kazuma Satoh, who sports a 1.99 ERA while leading the farm in IP. Satoh has both more IP and a lower ERA than Mukunoki on the farm, but while Mukunoki was a first round pick, Satoh was a developmental draft pick in 2019.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/orix_pitching_lab/orix_farm_fip_satoh.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">In the previous graph, you might have noticed one player with more IP than Mukunoki while still having a sub-100 FIP-. That would be Kazuma Satoh.</div> <p>Until this year, Satoh has never made an appearance on the top team. Even this year he spent most of the time of the farm. While many pitchers on Orix’s farm this year are just there to ramp up for the season or to get back into the groove before rejoining the top team, Satoh has been a consistent player on the farm, being only one of two pitchers there to have more than 40 IP. He never logged an ERA below 3.00 until this year, where he put up the aforementioned 1.99 ERA.</p> <p>Perhaps his performance on the farm, which got him a 82 FIP- and 90 xFIP-, finally earned him a call to the top team. He made his debut this June 9, where he blanked the Giants for 5 innings, giving up 1 hit, 2 walks, and recording 3 strikeouts. Unfortunately, in his next appearance, he gave up 1 ER over 2/3 IP in relief.</p> <p>The verdict is still not out for Kazuma Satoh as he’s hasn’t pitched much on the top team so far, but it’d be interesting to see how often they go back to him again later this year, if they do.</p> <h2 id="pitching-lab-goes-brrr-we-have-no-better-header-for-a-conclusion">Pitching lab goes brrr (We have no better header for a conclusion)</h2> <p>Before we conclude, we should probably add Kohei Azuma as an honorable mention. Like Sotani, he also only played less than 10 games last year, so this is his first year being in the rotation from the get-go.</p> <p>Anyway, that’s the list. We probably missed some good names to include here, and again, these players aren’t necessarily hidden gems. Just thought that these guys would be fun to keep tabs on this year.</p> <h3 id="data-sources">Data Sources:</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://bo-no05.hatenadiary.org/">ぼおのの日記</a></li> <li><a href="https://sp.baseball.findfriends.jp/">ベースボール週刊</a></li> <li><a href="https://baseballdata.jp/">baseballdata</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Ramos</name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="baseball"/><category term="npb"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[brrrrrr]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">empathic unsettlement in art spiegelman’s maus</title><link href="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/maus-empathic-unsettlement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="empathic unsettlement in art spiegelman’s maus"/><published>2024-06-09T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-06-09T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/maus-empathic-unsettlement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/maus-empathic-unsettlement/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was an essay I wrote for an English class when I was a freshmen in college around 2018-2019. I decided to cut down the title, add sections, and share it here.</em></p> <p><em>Content Warning: This essay discusses and displays scenes from Maus that some may find disturbing.</em></p> <h2 id="maus-and-empathic-unsettlement">Maus and empathic unsettlement</h2> <p>Much has been written about the Holocaust trauma representation in Art Spiegelman’s graphic novel Maus. Hirsch coins the term “post-memory” to describe the transmission of trauma through generations, which she contends is seen in Maus through its use of photographs.<d-footnote>See Hirsch (1992-1993), Hirsch (2008).</d-footnote> Costello meanwhile believes that the graphic novel recontextualizes the traumatic memory of the Shoah through “performative memorialization”.<d-footnote>See Costello (2006), 22-42.</d-footnote> One trauma concept yet to be applied to the comic is LaCapra’s “empathic unsettlement”, or the lack of full identification with victims.<d-footnote>See Lacapra (2001), 102.</d-footnote> This paper intends to bridge this gap and explore how Maus is connected to the concept. It contends that Maus is capable of producing empathic unsettlement in readers in two ways: 1) through the “psychic distance” resulting from the book’s frame story structure and 2) through the substitution of human beings with anthropomorphic animals. It should be noted that this paper does not assume the response of readers to be empathic unsettlement, as doing so would lead to an affective fallacy, but rather argues that the comic has factors in play which may arouse such a reaction.</p> <p>This thesis statement is proven through two parts. First, a summary of Maus is given, based on the edition published by Pantheon Books in two volumes, Maus: A Survivor’s Tale - My Father Bleeds History and Maus: A Survivor’s Tale - And Here My Troubles Began. Following the summary is a close reading of Maus to show how its frame story structure, psychic distance, and use of animals promote empathic unsettlement. Literary terms and other concepts mentioned in the discussion will be formally defined before use in analysis.</p> <p>Maus follows Jewish cartoonist Art “Artie” Spiegelman as he produces a comic about how his father Vladek experienced the Holocaust. Art interviews his father over a series of visits in the 1980s to better understand the events to portray, and the setting shifts to the 1930s to 1940s whenever Vladek recounts his past. Vladek narrates how he met his wife Anja and how the two of them were displaced to the ghettos, hid from the Nazis, and were imprisoned in Auschwitz until the end of World War II. All of this is intercut with present day events such as Art taking Vladek to the hospital or the two of them walking to the bank. Eventually, Vladek passes away and the first volume of Maus becomes published. Maus ends at a time before Vladek’s death, with the Shoah survivor describing his reunion with Anja after Auschwitz to Art.</p> <p>In arguing how Maus exemplifies empathic unsettlement, it is important to first formally explain the term. Aside from being a lack of full identification with victims, LaCapra writes that empathic unsettlement is a form of empathy that may result in trauma that is “secondary” or “muted.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> This is due to LaCapra stressing the major difference between the experience of Holocaust victims and recipients of their testimonies. Essentially, those whose experience of the Holocaust is only through testimonies cannot be considered as traumatized as the victims themselves, hence the former cannot fully identify with the latter.</p> <h2 id="frame-story-structure-and-psychic-distance">Frame-story structure and psychic distance</h2> <p>One way empathic unsettlement can be seen in Maus is through the presence of a psychic distance. Psychic distance is a term coined by Gardner to describe the distance from the text felt by the reader.<d-footnote>See Gardner (1984), 111.</d-footnote> This paper contends that psychic distance can be seen in Maus due to its frame story structure, or “a story which contains another story or series of stories” according to Clute’s and Grant’s <em>Encyclopedia of Fantasy</em>.<d-footnote>See Clute, Grant (1999), 365.</d-footnote> Maus evidently uses such a structure as Vladek’s story is not told directly but rather is inserted into a larger narrative as an interview conducted by Art. By framing Vladek’s story as an interview with a separate protagonist, psychic distance is implied between the narrative and the reader due to the distracting topic changes, which are a part and parcel of interviews, that often disrupt Vladek’s narrative.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-066-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-066-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-066-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-066.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-067-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-067-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-067-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-067.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Vladek's past is framed as an interview in the present, which is often interrupted. This creates a "psychic distance" between the reader and Vladek's experiences. </div> <p>One evidence of this is how in numerous instances throughout Maus, Vladek changes the topic of the discussion to his strained marriage with his second wife Mala. Sometimes this is unintentional, such as when reminiscing about Anja, he starts comparing her to Mala.<d-footnote>See Maus II: A Survivor's Tale: And Here My Troubles Began, 25.</d-footnote> Other times, he intentionally stays off topic to complain about Mala to Art, as he claims he “haven’t with whom else to talk.”<d-footnote>See Maus I: A Survivor's Tale: My Father Bleeds History, 67.</d-footnote></p> <p>Whether intentional or unintentional, the fact remains that Vladek’s narrative is repeatedly interrupted. This is a thought shared with Brown, who writes that Maus, being an “oral history account and also an account of oral history”, frames Vladek’s history and often disrupts it through the relationship between the interviewee and interviewer.<d-footnote>See Brown (1993), 1669.</d-footnote> Because it is repeatedly disrupted, Vladek’s recollection can then be considered “further away from audiences” or more difficult to properly observe, producing the aforementioned psychic distance. This psychic distance resulting from the framed history leads to the book’s represented trauma not being directly witnessed and instead being “secondary”, which is in line with LaCapra’s empathic unsettlement.</p> <h2 id="contrast-in-anthropomorphic-animals">Contrast in anthropomorphic animals</h2> <p>Empathic unsettlement also seems to be implied through Spiegelman’s use of anthropomorphic animals. Throughout almost the entire graphic novel, animals take the role of humans. Jews are mice, Germans are cats, Americans are dogs, the French are frogs, and so on and so forth. This paper argues that the use of animals contributes to the potential arousal of empathic unsettlement through the stark contrast between qualities associated with humanoid animals and those of the trauma represented by the book.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0 mx-auto"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-108-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-108-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-108-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-108.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The typical association between anthropomorphic animals and fantasy and humor dampens the traumatic events in Maus by portraying characters as animals. </div> <p>The anthropomorphism of animals is commonly found in children’s literature, and among Markowsky’s explanations for this are the emboldening of fantasy elements and humor.<d-footnote>See Markowsky (1975), 461.</d-footnote> Markowsky appears justified in these arguments in examples of the fantastical talking rabbits of <em>Rabbit Hill</em> and the humorous Toad of <em>The Wind in the Willows</em>.<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> However, when anthropomorphic animals are used in Maus, there remains nothing fantastical or humorous about the horrors Vladek experienced, which include witnessing a Nazi swinging a child against a wall in the ghetto<d-footnote>See Maus I: A Survivor's Tale: My Father Bleeds History, 108.</d-footnote> and walking on the heads of corpses crowding the lavatory corridor in Auschwitz.<d-footnote>See Maus II: A Survivor's Tale: And Here My Troubles Began, 95.</d-footnote></p> <p>The personal thoughts of both father and son further reflect the tragic nature of the events that the former had to endure. Although thanking God in the past that his first son Richieu did not suffer the fate of the child swung against the wall (although in reality Richieu did indeed die, albeit through poison),<d-footnote>See Maus I: A Survivor's Tale: My Father Bleeds History, 108.</d-footnote> Vladek in the present ruminates how in Auschwitz, “God didn’t come.” This change in perspective on God between the past and the present implies that the trauma experienced at the camp was enough to disturb Vladek’s faith. When Art’s wife comments “It’s a miracle he [Vladek] survived,” Art replies “Uh-huh. But in some ways he didn’t.”<d-footnote>See Maus II: A Survivor's Tale: And Here My Troubles Began, 90.</d-footnote> With this statement Art may be referring to how his father continues to be haunted by the Shoah. After all, Vladek has been moaning in his sleep since as early as Art’s childhood.<d-footnote>Ibid., 74.</d-footnote></p> <p>The fact that both Vladek and Art allude to the intensity of the father’s psychological trauma seemingly corroborate the utter cruelty of Vladek’s experiences. The grim tone of the events Vladek underwent is evidently far different from the fantasy and humor associated with anthropomorphic animals. These lighter elements can be seen as a counterweight to the darker elements of trauma to make the horrors of Maus more removed from audiences. In writing about Maus, although not connecting it to empathic unsettlement, LaCapra has a similar idea, describing the use of animal figures as a distancing device.<d-footnote>See LaCapra (1998), 169.</d-footnote> By lessening the impact of trauma with anthropomorphic animals which are associated with more positive qualities, the trauma represented in Maus appears to be “muted”, once again coinciding with the concept of empathic unsettlement.</p> <h2 id="never-fully-identifying">Never fully identifying</h2> <p>In conclusion, this paper, while not assuming the reactions of readers, asserts that any empathy aroused in readers by Maus may be empathic unsettlement. It argues this through revealing how the trauma expressed by the work is secondary (due to a psychic distance resulting from its frame story structure) and muted (due to the contrasting nature of animal use in literature and the traumatic events covered in the book). The study of empathic unsettlement is significant as LaCapra believes that such a type of empathy prevents objectification of suffering while still allowing exposure to it.<d-footnote>See LaCapra (2001), 102.</d-footnote> All this means to say is that in cases where the only knowledge one has of the Shoah is through testimonies of actual victims, the most desirable way for them to respond would be to remain empathically unsettled. Never fully identifying, but nonetheless, still understanding.</p> <d-cite key="hirsch1992family" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="hirsch2008generation" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="costello2006history" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="lacapra2001writing" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="gardner1984art" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="clute199encyclopedia" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="spiegelman1991maus" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="spiegelman1986maus" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="brown1993maus" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="markowsky1975anthropomorphism" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="lacapra1998history" hidden=""></d-cite>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Ramos</name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="comics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[how a frame-story structure and anthropomorphism prevent full identification with victims of trauma]]></summary></entry></feed>