<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-06-18T12:55:15+09:00</updated><id>https://ramos-ramos.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ramos &amp;amp; Ramos</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">orix pitching lab goes brrr: 5 new(ish) buffaloes pitchers to keep an eye on this year</title><link href="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/orix-pitching-lab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="orix pitching lab goes brrr: 5 new(ish) buffaloes pitchers to keep an eye on this year"/><published>2024-06-13T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-06-13T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/orix-pitching-lab</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/orix-pitching-lab/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/orix_pitching_lab-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/orix_pitching_lab-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/orix_pitching_lab-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/orix_pitching_lab.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="welcome-to-the-pitching-lab">Welcome to the pitching lab</h2> <p>No one was particularly worried about the Orix Buffaloes pitching when they posted back-to-back-to-back Sawamura Award winner, PL triple crown winner, and PL MVP Yoshinobu Yamamoto, primarily because they have a pitching lab. Just last year fireballer Shunpeita Yamashita made his top team debut and went on to win 2023 PL ROY. Not to mention they also have 2021 ROY Hiroya Miyagi, who prior to straining his chest was carrying a 1.89 FIP and a 24.3 K-BB% this year. Kohei Azuma even climbed his way to the top team as a developmental draft pick, becoming the first pitcher to start their career with winning 7 consecutive decisions en route to starting Game 3 of the 2023 Japan Series.</p> <p>As a pitching lab, the Buffaloes are more or less continuing to put out arms. Whether they’ll all pan out we’ve yet to see, but here are five new(ish) Orix pitchers that might be interesting to keep on eye for the rest of 2024.</p> <p>Some disclaimers before we continue:</p> <ol> <li> <p>None of these names are surprising. If you follow <a href="https://twitter.com/yakyucosmo">Yakyu Cosmopolitan</a>, you’ll have definitely heard of these names. It’s still interesting however that these are not players who played regularly on the top team last season.</p> </li> <li> <p>I am far, far from anything even remotely resembling a player evaluator. Don’t expect any cool discussions about the shape of their fastball or how they improved their mechanics this offseason or anything like that (I certainly wish I was smart enough to talk about those things).</p> </li> <li> <p>Just to be clear, I’m not running an Orix fan page here. I like players, not teams, and Orix just happens to produce a lot of players I find interesting.</p> </li> </ol> <h2 id="1-the-obvious-one-ryuhei-sotani">1. The obvious one: Ryuhei Sotani</h2> <div class="row mt-3 l-screen"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/sotani-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/sotani-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/sotani-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/sotani.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Where else to start other than Ryuhei Sotani. Yakyu Cosmopolitan had Sotani pegged as the No. 3 overall prospect and Orix’s No. 1 prospect coming into this season, although he’s already graduated by now.</p> <center> <div class="jekyll-twitter-plugin"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="ja" dir="ltr">My Top 50 NPB Prospects in 2024<br/><br/>個人的な2024年NPBプロスペクト ランキング <a href="https://t.co/kXDfqSFGSE">pic.twitter.com/kXDfqSFGSE</a></p>&mdash; Yakyu Cosmopolitan (@yakyucosmo) <a href="https://twitter.com/yakyucosmo/status/1742538964089901430?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 3, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> </div> </center> <p>Sotani was Orix’s first round draft pick in 2022, and started only 7 games in 2023. This season marks his first a full-fledged member of the rotation, where he’s been helping Anderson Espinoza and Luis Castillo carry the load for an Orix rotation that has lost Yamamoto (MLB), Miyagi (injured), Yamashita (who was working out some things on the farm, but just came back recently), Yamasaki (Nippon-Ham), and Yamaoka (injured to start the season).</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/orix_rotation.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="550px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Sotani has been one of the best domestic starters in Orix's rotation with Miyagi out.</div> <p>Of the rotation they’ve had in May since Miyagi’s injury, he’s been the best domestic Orix starter with at least 30 IP in terms of FIP, xFIP, K%, and BB% (Miyagi would lead if he was still in). He’s also pushed his K/9 to 9.2 thanks to his June 11 start of 6 IP, 0 ER, 12 K. Needless to say, the kid is shoving.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/npb_lhp_fb.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Among lefities, minimum 100 fastball thrown, Sotani's fastball is in the 80th percentile in terms of velocity.</div> <p>What else makes Sotani so special, aside from being the latest Orix whiz kid? He throws 92 mph, which in Japan is apparently already quite good for a lefty. He’s 80th percentile in fastball velo for left handed pitchers with at least 100 fastballs thrown.</p> <p>All-in-all, Sotani looks to take the torch from Shunpeita Yamashita as the poster boy of the Orix pitching lab.</p> <h2 id="2-the-prospect-kyosuke-saito">2. The prospect: Kyosuke Saito</h2> <div class="row mt-3 l-screen"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/saito-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/saito-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/saito-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/saito.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/orix_starters.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="550" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Because he is not a full-time member of Orix's starting, Kyosuke Saito does not have innings under his belt. However in his very small sample size, he has been quite effective.</div> <p>If Ryuhei Sotani has already graduated, who is now Orix’s No. 1 prospect? That would be Kyosuke Saito, who was drafted two rounds after Sotani back in 2022. He pitched 4 IP in 2023, and has gotten more starts in 2024, where he a currently has a 0.47 ERA and 0.83 WHIP, and is holding opponents to a 0.373 OPS over a small sample size of 19 1/3 IP.</p> <p>His sub-1.00 ERA may last long as he’s got a 44.00 OFFB% on the top team and a 43.6 OFFB% as a starter on the farm in a similar sample size, but again these samples might be small.</p> <p>Saito’s still a prospect and as such may be expected to grow further still, but if he can maintain his current success and fully break out, perhaps we could be looking at the newest full-time member of the Orix rotation.</p> <h2 id="3-the-rookie-seiryu-kotajima">3. The rookie: Seiryu Kotajima</h2> <div class="row mt-3 l-screen"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/kotajima-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/kotajima-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/kotajima-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/kotajima.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Success from lower round draft picks aren’t unheard of, but they’re always interesting to see. Ryuhei Sotani was a first rounder, and Kyosuke Saito was a third rounder, but rookie Seiryu Kotajima is a 2023 sixth round draft pick who’s already finding playing time on the top team.</p> <p>Orix doesn’t only have elite starters, but they’ve also put out lights-out relievers as well, such as Yuki Udagawa and Soichiro Yamazaki. Udagawa and Yamazaki haven’t been playing as much this season, but Kotajima’s been holding down the fort in spectacular fashion, starting his career with 21 scoreless pitching appearances. While a 0.00 ERA obviously isn’t sustainable, his 3.06 FIP is still good for a 94 FIP-.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/orix_bullpen.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Even if his 0.00 ERA can't continue forever, Kotajima's FIP is still competitive among Orix bullpen arms and he's consuming innings while doing it. Only an NPB veteran (Kazutomo Iguchi) and an MLB veteran (Andres Machado) players have better FIP and more innings. Remember, Kotajima is keeping up as a rookie.</div> <p>Even if Seiryu Kotajima may be experiencing some luck right now, it looks like Orix have found a new shut down option for their bullpen this season.</p> <h2 id="4-the-comeback-kid-ren-mukunoki">4. The comeback kid: Ren Mukunoki</h2> <div class="row mt-3 l-screen"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/mukunoki-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/mukunoki-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/mukunoki-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/mukunoki.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Orix’s 2021 first round draft pick Ren Mukunoki started hot out the gate in 2022, pitching to a 1.02 ERA across four starts (one being one out away from a no-hitter) before needing Tommy John surgery.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/orix_farm_fip_mukunoki.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">Mukunoki has been hard at work on the farm since coming back from Tommy John.</div> <p>Mukunoki’s now back in 2024 and has posted a 2.08 ERA, 2.62 FIP, 2.97 xFIP, and a 5% BB% on the farm across 37 IP. However, he unfortunately couldn’t replicate that success in a lone start on the top team, giving up 4 ER over 3 IP.</p> <p>While we still need to see more of him on the top team, his underlying numbers hopefully show that he has indeed returned to form, making him a player to keep on eye on for the rest of 2024.</p> <h2 id="5-the-unproven-kazuma-satoh">5. The unproven: Kazuma Satoh</h2> <div class="row mt-3 l-screen"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/satoh-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/satoh-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/satoh-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/orix_pitching_lab/satoh.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>If you thought Orix finding relative success with a sixth rounder was impressive, wait until you hear about Kazuma Satoh.</p> <p>There are only two people who have pitched more innings than Ren Mukunoki on the farm, and one of them has a 3.78 ERA. The other one is Kazuma Satoh, who sports a 1.99 ERA while leading the farm in IP. Satoh has both more IP and a lower ERA than Mukunoki on the farm, but while Mukunoki was a first round pick, Satoh was a developmental draft pick in 2019.</p> <div class="l-body" align="center"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/orix_farm_fip_satoh.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <div class="caption">In the previous graph, you might have noticed one player with more IP than Mukunoki while still having a sub-100 FIP-. That would be Kazuma Satoh.</div> <p>Until this year, Satoh has never made an appearance on the top team. Even this year he spent most of the time of the farm. While many pitchers on Orix’s farm this year are just there to ramp up for the season or to get back into the groove before rejoining the top team, Satoh has been a consistent player on the farm, being only one of two pitchers there to have more than 40 IP. He never logged an ERA below 3.00 until this year, where he put up the aforementioned 1.99 ERA.</p> <p>Perhaps his performance on the farm, which got him a 82 FIP- and 90 xFIP-, finally earned him a call to the top team. He made his debut this June 9, where he blanked the Giants for 5 innings, giving up 1 hit, 2 walks, and recording 3 strikeouts. Unfortunately, in his next appearance, he gave up 1 ER over 2/3 IP in relief.</p> <p>The verdict is still not out for Kazuma Satoh as he’s hasn’t pitched much on the top team so far, but it’d be interesting to see how often they go back to him again later this year, if they do.</p> <h2 id="pitching-lab-goes-brrr-i-have-no-better-header-for-a-conclusion">Pitching lab goes brrr (I have no better header for a conclusion)</h2> <p>Before I conclude, I should probably add Kohei Azuma as an honorable mention. Like Sotani, he also only played less than 10 games last year, so this is his first year being in the rotation from the get-go.</p> <p>Anyway, that’s the list. I probably missed some good names to include here, and again, these players aren’t necessarily hidden gems. Just thought that these guys would be fun to keep tabs on this year.</p> <h3 id="data-sources">Data Sources:</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://bo-no05.hatenadiary.org/">ぼおのの日記</a></li> <li><a href="https://sp.baseball.findfriends.jp/">ベースボール週刊</a></li> <li><a href="https://baseballdata.jp/">baseballdata</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Ramos</name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="baseball"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[brrrrrr]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">empathic unsettlement in art spiegelman’s maus</title><link href="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/maus-empathic-unsettlement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="empathic unsettlement in art spiegelman’s maus"/><published>2024-06-09T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-06-09T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/maus-empathic-unsettlement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ramos-ramos.github.io/blog/2024/maus-empathic-unsettlement/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was an essay I wrote for an English class when I was a freshmen in college around 2018-2019. I decided to cut down the title, add sections, and share it here.</em></p> <p><em>Content Warning: This essay discusses and displays scenes from Maus that some may find disturbing.</em></p> <h2 id="maus-and-empathic-unsettlement">Maus and empathic unsettlement</h2> <p>Much has been written about the Holocaust trauma representation in Art Spiegelman’s graphic novel Maus. Hirsch coins the term “post-memory” to describe the transmission of trauma through generations, which she contends is seen in Maus through its use of photographs.<d-footnote>See Hirsch (1992-1993), Hirsch (2008).</d-footnote> Costello meanwhile believes that the graphic novel recontextualizes the traumatic memory of the Shoah through “performative memorialization”.<d-footnote>See Costello (2006), 22-42.</d-footnote> One trauma concept yet to be applied to the comic is LaCapra’s “empathic unsettlement”, or the lack of full identification with victims.<d-footnote>See Lacapra (2001), 102.</d-footnote> This paper intends to bridge this gap and explore how Maus is connected to the concept. It contends that Maus is capable of producing empathic unsettlement in readers in two ways: 1) through the “psychic distance” resulting from the book’s frame story structure and 2) through the substitution of human beings with anthropomorphic animals. It should be noted that this paper does not assume the response of readers to be empathic unsettlement, as doing so would lead to an affective fallacy, but rather argues that the comic has factors in play which may arouse such a reaction.</p> <p>This thesis statement is proven through two parts. First, a summary of Maus is given, based on the edition published by Pantheon Books in two volumes, Maus: A Survivor’s Tale - My Father Bleeds History and Maus: A Survivor’s Tale - And Here My Troubles Began. Following the summary is a close reading of Maus to show how its frame story structure, psychic distance, and use of animals promote empathic unsettlement. Literary terms and other concepts mentioned in the discussion will be formally defined before use in analysis.</p> <p>Maus follows Jewish cartoonist Art “Artie” Spiegelman as he produces a comic about how his father Vladek experienced the Holocaust. Art interviews his father over a series of visits in the 1980s to better understand the events to portray, and the setting shifts to the 1930s to 1940s whenever Vladek recounts his past. Vladek narrates how he met his wife Anja and how the two of them were displaced to the ghettos, hid from the Nazis, and were imprisoned in Auschwitz until the end of World War II. All of this is intercut with present day events such as Art taking Vladek to the hospital or the two of them walking to the bank. Eventually, Vladek passes away and the first volume of Maus becomes published. Maus ends at a time before Vladek’s death, with the Shoah survivor describing his reunion with Anja after Auschwitz to Art.</p> <p>In arguing how Maus exemplifies empathic unsettlement, it is important to first formally explain the term. Aside from being a lack of full identification with victims, LaCapra writes that empathic unsettlement is a form of empathy that may result in trauma that is “secondary” or “muted.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> This is due to LaCapra stressing the major difference between the experience of Holocaust victims and recipients of their testimonies. Essentially, those whose experience of the Holocaust is only through testimonies cannot be considered as traumatized as the victims themselves, hence the former cannot fully identify with the latter.</p> <h2 id="frame-story-structure-and-psychic-distance">Frame-story structure and psychic distance</h2> <p>One way empathic unsettlement can be seen in Maus is through the presence of a psychic distance. Psychic distance is a term coined by Gardner to describe the distance from the text felt by the reader.<d-footnote>See Gardner (1984), 111.</d-footnote> This paper contends that psychic distance can be seen in Maus due to its frame story structure, or “a story which contains another story or series of stories” according to Clute’s and Grant’s <em>Encyclopedia of Fantasy</em>.<d-footnote>See Clute, Grant (1999), 365.</d-footnote> Maus evidently uses such a structure as Vladek’s story is not told directly but rather is inserted into a larger narrative as an interview conducted by Art. By framing Vladek’s story as an interview with a separate protagonist, psychic distance is implied between the narrative and the reader due to the distracting topic changes, which are a part and parcel of interviews, that often disrupt Vladek’s narrative.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-066-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-066-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-066-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-066.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-067-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-067-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-067-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-067.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Vladek's past is framed as an interview in the present, which is often interrupted. This creates a "psychic distance" between the reader and Vladek's experiences. </div> <p>One evidence of this is how in numerous instances throughout Maus, Vladek changes the topic of the discussion to his strained marriage with his second wife Mala. Sometimes this is unintentional, such as when reminiscing about Anja, he starts comparing her to Mala.<d-footnote>See Maus II: A Survivor's Tale: And Here My Troubles Began, 25.</d-footnote> Other times, he intentionally stays off topic to complain about Mala to Art, as he claims he “haven’t with whom else to talk.”<d-footnote>See Maus I: A Survivor's Tale: My Father Bleeds History, 67.</d-footnote></p> <p>Whether intentional or unintentional, the fact remains that Vladek’s narrative is repeatedly interrupted. This is a thought shared with Brown, who writes that Maus, being an “oral history account and also an account of oral history”, frames Vladek’s history and often disrupts it through the relationship between the interviewee and interviewer.<d-footnote>See Brown (1993), 1669.</d-footnote> Because it is repeatedly disrupted, Vladek’s recollection can then be considered “further away from audiences” or more difficult to properly observe, producing the aforementioned psychic distance. This psychic distance resulting from the framed history leads to the book’s represented trauma not being directly witnessed and instead being “secondary”, which is in line with LaCapra’s empathic unsettlement.</p> <h2 id="contrast-in-anthropomorphic-animals">Contrast in anthropomorphic animals</h2> <p>Empathic unsettlement also seems to be implied through Spiegelman’s use of anthropomorphic animals. Throughout almost the entire graphic novel, animals take the role of humans. Jews are mice, Germans are cats, Americans are dogs, the French are frogs, and so on and so forth. This paper argues that the use of animals contributes to the potential arousal of empathic unsettlement through the stark contrast between qualities associated with humanoid animals and those of the trauma represented by the book.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0 mx-auto"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-108-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-108-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/maus/maus-1-108-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/maus/maus-1-108.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The typical association between anthropomorphic animals and fantasy and humor dampens the traumatic events in Maus by portraying characters as animals. </div> <p>The anthropomorphism of animals is commonly found in children’s literature, and among Markowsky’s explanations for this are the emboldening of fantasy elements and humor.<d-footnote>See Markowsky (1975), 461.</d-footnote> Markowsky appears justified in these arguments in examples of the fantastical talking rabbits of <em>Rabbit Hill</em> and the humorous Toad of <em>The Wind in the Willows</em>.<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> However, when anthropomorphic animals are used in Maus, there remains nothing fantastical or humorous about the horrors Vladek experienced, which include witnessing a Nazi swinging a child against a wall in the ghetto<d-footnote>See Maus I: A Survivor's Tale: My Father Bleeds History, 108.</d-footnote> and walking on the heads of corpses crowding the lavatory corridor in Auschwitz.<d-footnote>See Maus II: A Survivor's Tale: And Here My Troubles Began, 95.</d-footnote></p> <p>The personal thoughts of both father and son further reflect the tragic nature of the events that the former had to endure. Although thanking God in the past that his first son Richieu did not suffer the fate of the child swung against the wall (although in reality Richieu did indeed die, albeit through poison),<d-footnote>See Maus I: A Survivor's Tale: My Father Bleeds History, 108.</d-footnote> Vladek in the present ruminates how in Auschwitz, “God didn’t come.” This change in perspective on God between the past and the present implies that the trauma experienced at the camp was enough to disturb Vladek’s faith. When Art’s wife comments “It’s a miracle he [Vladek] survived,” Art replies “Uh-huh. But in some ways he didn’t.”<d-footnote>See Maus II: A Survivor's Tale: And Here My Troubles Began, 90.</d-footnote> With this statement Art may be referring to how his father continues to be haunted by the Shoah. After all, Vladek has been moaning in his sleep since as early as Art’s childhood.<d-footnote>Ibid., 74.</d-footnote></p> <p>The fact that both Vladek and Art allude to the intensity of the father’s psychological trauma seemingly corroborate the utter cruelty of Vladek’s experiences. The grim tone of the events Vladek underwent is evidently far different from the fantasy and humor associated with anthropomorphic animals. These lighter elements can be seen as a counterweight to the darker elements of trauma to make the horrors of Maus more removed from audiences. In writing about Maus, although not connecting it to empathic unsettlement, LaCapra has a similar idea, describing the use of animal figures as a distancing device.<d-footnote>See LaCapra (1998), 169.</d-footnote> By lessening the impact of trauma with anthropomorphic animals which are associated with more positive qualities, the trauma represented in Maus appears to be “muted”, once again coinciding with the concept of empathic unsettlement.</p> <h2 id="never-fully-identifying">Never fully identifying</h2> <p>In conclusion, this paper, while not assuming the reactions of readers, asserts that any empathy aroused in readers by Maus may be empathic unsettlement. It argues this through revealing how the trauma expressed by the work is secondary (due to a psychic distance resulting from its frame story structure) and muted (due to the contrasting nature of animal use in literature and the traumatic events covered in the book). The study of empathic unsettlement is significant as LaCapra believes that such a type of empathy prevents objectification of suffering while still allowing exposure to it.<d-footnote>See LaCapra (2001), 102.</d-footnote> All this means to say is that in cases where the only knowledge one has of the Shoah is through testimonies of actual victims, the most desirable way for them to respond would be to remain empathically unsettled. Never fully identifying, but nonetheless, still understanding.</p> <d-cite key="hirsch1992family" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="hirsch2008generation" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="costello2006history" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="lacapra2001writing" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="gardner1984art" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="clute199encyclopedia" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="spiegelman1991maus" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="spiegelman1986maus" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="brown1993maus" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="markowsky1975anthropomorphism" hidden=""></d-cite> <d-cite key="lacapra1998history" hidden=""></d-cite>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Ramos</name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="comics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[how a frame-story structure and anthropomorphism prevent full identification with victims of trauma]]></summary></entry></feed>